<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-12T18:04:52+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>I am a professional Backend developer who is also good at Deep Learning. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why piracy should be avoided?</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2025/why-piracy-should-be-avoided/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why piracy should be avoided?"/><published>2025-02-23T09:53:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-23T09:53:00+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2025/why-piracy-should-be-avoided</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2025/why-piracy-should-be-avoided/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="is-it-moral-to-pirate-stuff">Is it moral to pirate stuff?</h1> <p>I have been wondering about this question since early 2020. I never encouraged piracy (may be I did unintentionally and I seek Allah’s forgiveness) even before 2020 but I used to pirate books and software prior to that myself (May Allah forgive me for this as well). But once I got familiarised with open source and linux world I started to question my past.</p> <p>In fact, I reached out to my teachers as well because I was in this <strong>congnitive dissonance</strong>. I could not digest the fact that <em>whatever I am learning is by stealing the works (books) of other humans</em> and whether any earning based on this knowledge can be classified as <strong>halal rizq</strong> or not.</p> <p>Today, If you are feeling the same and want to learn more about this issue then you should continue reading this article. <em>I would like to add a disclaimer here that I am not an expert on the subject of Islamic Jurisprudence so take my opinions with a pinch of salt.</em></p> <h2 id="is-priacy-stealing">Is priacy stealing?</h2> <p>Yes, Piracy is stealing. What’s stealing? In my view, stealing is to take or use any possession (material or immaterial) of a person without his / her explicit permission. Material possessions can be things like books or software written by someone and immaterial posessions can be things like ideas of a person.</p> <p>So, when you are downloading some software or book which is an intellectual property of that person; are you doing so with his / her explicit permission? If the answer to this question is <strong>NO</strong> then my friend you have been doing stealing intentionally or unintentionallly. What should you do now? <strong>Taubah</strong>: a) Recognize that what you were doing was wrong. b) Don’t do it again and if you can then undo the damage. c) A firm resolution with yourself that you will not get back to it again.</p> <h2 id="what-does-muslim-scholars-say-about-piracy">What does Muslim scholars say about piracy?</h2> <p>Almost all Ulema would agree that a person should not mass distribute material or immaterial possesion of a person without his / her explicit permission irrespective of that fact whether you acquired that possesion by purchase or not with one exception; that is if they agreed upon this during purchase.</p> <h3 id="the-contract">The Contract</h3> <p>If during purchase it was agreed upon by both parties a) buyer and b) seller that the buyer has the right to mass produce it then obviously its fine to share it (again depending on the exact contract terms). <strong>Buying something from someone is basically a form of a contract</strong>. So the terms of the contract must be respected and if there is an ambiguity then it should be rectified by discussion rather than exploiting that ambiguity for your advantage.</p> <h3 id="can-i-share-a-book-or-software-that-i-purchased-with-some-of-my-friends">Can I share a book or software that I purchased with some of my friends?</h3> <p>If during purchase it was decided then yes you can. If it was not decided then there is an ambiguity and you should contact the owner and clarify the situation and ask for explicit permission before doing so.</p> <h3 id="does-me-buying-a-book-or-software-makes-me-the-owner">Does me buying a book or software makes me the owner?</h3> <p>Depends on the contract of purchase. Again, if there is an ambiguity you should ask the person you bought it from. Ideally, this should be discussed before the purchase to avoid such inconveniences and problems.</p> <h3 id="mass-distribution-is-unethical-and-immoral">Mass distribution is unethical and immoral</h3> <p>So far, we have established that mass distributing someone’s work (for both commercial or non-commercial purposes) without his / her explicit permission even if you have purchased it, is not a moral thing to do.</p> <h2 id="personal-non-commercial-use-of-pirated-stuff">Personal non-commercial use of pirated stuff</h2> <p>The trickier part where Muslim scholars are divided is whether or not can you download something that is available for free publicly on internet for non-commercial personal use?</p> <p>Some Muslim Scholars that <strong>allow downloading books and software from internet for personal use</strong> argue that <strong>you were not the one who stole those books and published them on internet</strong>. So as long as <strong>you are not mass distributing them the proof of burden on the Judgement Day will not be on you but instead on the person who put them on internet at the first place</strong>. It is to be noted that these scholars allow only <strong>non-commercial personal use</strong> with the condition that you will not be mass distributing or sharing them in any shape or form.</p> <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=itBNcwRpvE4" target="_blank"><img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/itBNcwRpvE4/0.jpg" alt="IMAGE ALT TEXT HERE" width="240" height="180" border="10"/></a></p> <p>There are Muslim Scholars which <strong>discourage downloading pirated books and software</strong> from internet even for personal use. They argue that your <strong>downloading of such material encourages the person running such piracy sites</strong> to publish more of such material and content because he is getting attraction and traffic on his site which he can then monetize.</p> <p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=cQaoFgg0u-o" target="_blank"><img src="http://img.youtube.com/vi/cQaoFgg0u-o/0.jpg" alt="IMAGE ALT TEXT HERE" width="240" height="180" border="10"/></a></p> <p>In short, according to some scholars you can download books or softwares from internet that are pirated copies of someone’s else work as long as you dont mass distribute or share them with anyone else and use them personally in non-commercially way only. There are other scholars who totally discourage this because your downloading of priated stuff encourages the site owner to continue piracy or do more piracy. So, by downloading such material you are also contributing your part in this sin.</p> <p>So, if you are pirating stuff for personal please don’t encourage others to do the same and <strong>if someone is asking for a resource</strong> make sure you <strong>point him to a legitimate sources</strong> and <strong>let him decide if he wants to pirate it or purchase it</strong>. Don’t do the devil’s work of sharing pirated links! You might get questioned about this on the Day of Judgement. So be mindful of the actions you do.</p> <h2 id="why-pirate-stuff-when-there-are-free-alternatives-available">Why pirate stuff when there are free alternatives available?</h2> <p>Why at the first place you need to pirate something that has a free legitimate alternative available that you can download for free? Why go down the wrong path? Ask yourself this next time when you are about to pirate something.</p> <h2 id="dont-sail-the-black-ship">Don’t sail the black ship</h2> <p>Here are some tips that can help you live a life that is free of piracy:</p> <ul> <li>Use Linux instead of Windows. Linux is a free and open source operating system and by switching to it you will be saving yourself from a lot of trouble of pirating stuff.</li> <li>Pirated software most of the times have malwares in them that can cause harm to your system. By switching to open source softwares not only you will be avoiding this potential harm but in fact you will get much better performance as proprietory software has too much bloatware and adware in it.</li> <li>Try to find books with Creative Commons license. These are the books that author has explicitly given permission for to use for free. There are many types of Creative Commons licenses some even allow commercial use. Learn about these licenses.</li> <li>For tutorials there are tons of MOOC (Massive Open Online Courses) sites that offer free quality content with some limitation. For example you might have to pay if you want to get a certificate but content itself would be free.Youtube is also a great platform to learn new stuff.</li> <li>When purchasing an item especially digital ones .i.e. softwares &amp; ebooks ask explicitly from the author whether he is transferring ownerships rights to you or not? This will save you from a lot of problems down the line in future.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="free and open source software"/><category term="piracy"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="foss"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is it moral to pirate stuff?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mastodon and Fediverse</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/mastodon-and-fediverse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mastodon and Fediverse"/><published>2024-05-29T18:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T18:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/mastodon-and-fediverse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/mastodon-and-fediverse/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-potential-twitter-alternative-for-global-muslim-ummah">A potential twitter alternative for global muslim ummah</h2> <h3 id="what-is-mastodon">What is mastodon?</h3> <p>Mastodon is a free and open source decentralised twitter like microblogging social media platform where a user can toot (tweet) and share it with his followers.</p> <h3 id="what-does-free-and-open-source-mean">What does free and open source mean?</h3> <p>Free and open source software abbreviated as FOSS is a software whose source code is publicly available for anyone to modify, edit and publish.</p> <h3 id="what-does-decentralised-mean">What does Decentralised mean?</h3> <p>Decentralisation is a concept which means a property, software, technology, asset or database which is not owned by a single entity rather it is controlled and managed by a community of people and they are free to administer it as they please. Decentralisation is the opposite of centralised software, property, technology, asset or database. In centralization the asset is controlled by a single entity or organisation. For example Meta controls facebook, Google controls youtube &amp; open ai controls chat gpt.</p> <h3 id="what-does-fediverse-mean">What does fediverse mean?</h3> <p>Fediverse is a collection of decentralised software which aims to replace traditional social media platforms.</p> <p>Traditional Social Media platform Fediverse alternative Twitter Mastodon Youtube Peertube Instagram Pixel Fed Reddit Lemmy Facebook Hubzilla / Friendica</p> <h3 id="what-benefits-decentralised-tech-can-have">What benefits decentralised tech can have?</h3> <p>As it is not owned by a single entity the community can decide the rules as they please so the centralised entity which is non-existing can not dictate any rules or policy. In other words, our platform, our rules. No more shadow banning and censorship of ideas.</p> <p>What are some problems with existing traditional social media platforms?</p> <p>Existing social media platforms are owned by a single entity, corporation or organisation and they allow only those narratives that suit them and suppress the voice of the opposing side. Or governments / law enforcement agencies can force them to take down some content of people who are criticising state policies.</p> <h3 id="how-can-we-use-mastodon-to-connect-muslims-globally">How can we use mastodon to connect muslims globally?</h3> <p>As Mastodon is free and open source which means we can self host an instance of mastodon on our server and potentially we can invite anyone from all over the globe to join our platform and connect with us and exchange their ideas.</p> <h3 id="what-costs-are-associated-with-self-hosting-mastodon">What costs are associated with self hosting mastodon?</h3> <p>The upfront cost which is associated with self hosting mastodon is of hosting server. We don’t need any development initially as code is already available and we can go live at any moment but we might need a few people or a small team to constantly manage, support and maintain our server. We can hire dedicated people or have volunteers for this. Now coming back to the cost, as per our initial estimate we need only $20 to $25 to host a small instance of mastodon which can accommodate around 800 active users.</p> <h3 id="shall-we-abandon-traditional-social-media-platforms-and-switch-to-fediverse">Shall we abandon traditional social media platforms and switch to fediverse?</h3> <p>Ideally yes we should invite more and more people to fediverse but realistically speaking this is not possible because traditional social media platforms have already created a user base or fan base and most people will be reluctant to shift to fediverse because they might not gain the same traction on fediverse as they are getting on traditional social media. But to connect Muslim ummah at a global level we can use fediverse as a tool and side by side we can keep using traditional social media platforms as well to raise our issues to the global community.</p> <h3 id="how-are-we-going-to-self-sustain-this-platform">How are we going to self-sustain this platform?</h3>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Fediverse"/><category term="Mastodon"/><category term="mastodon"/><category term="fediverse"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A potential twitter alternative for global muslim ummah]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Signal as alternative of WhatsApp</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/signal-as-alternative-of-whatsapp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Signal as alternative of WhatsApp"/><published>2024-02-23T17:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-23T17:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/signal-as-alternative-of-whatsapp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/signal-as-alternative-of-whatsapp/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="signal-messaging-app">Signal Messaging app</h2> <p>When we look for alternatives to WhatsApp, one app which suddenly comes on the table of options is Signal.</p> <p>Pros:</p> <ul> <li>Gold standard encryption, even WhatsApp uses it.</li> <li>You can communicate without exposing your phone number.</li> </ul> <p>Cons:</p> <ul> <li>There is no explicit limit to the number of people that can be added to a Signal group chat. However, if the group becomes very large, it can become difficult to manage, and you may notice that messages take a bit longer to send. Update: There is a limit of 1k members, not sure if performance wise it will still be a problem or not.</li> <li>No threads / channels support as we have in discord, slack &amp; MS Teams. Threads &amp; Channels helps to organize discussion on different topics / issues.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="free and open source software"/><category term="messaging apps"/><category term="signal"/><category term="whatsapp"/><category term="foss"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Signal Messaging app]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to copy or move millions of files concurrently in linux</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/how-to-copy-or-move-millions-of-files-concurrently-in-linux/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to copy or move millions of files concurrently in linux"/><published>2024-01-04T13:29:14+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-04T13:29:14+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/how-to-copy-or-move-millions-of-files-concurrently-in-linux</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2024/how-to-copy-or-move-millions-of-files-concurrently-in-linux/"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes, you need to copy or move files from one drive to another. Copying or moving files using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cp</code> / <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mv</code> one by one can take considerable time some times days and weeks depending upon number of files, size of individual file and disk speed.</p> <p>Here’s one way to speed up this process by using which you can copy / move millions of files concurrently from one directory to another in linux utilizing all CPU threads.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>find . -type f | parallel --bar cp {} /path/to/destination
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Break down of this command:</p> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">find . -type f</code> means find all files in current directory. We then pipe this list to a tool called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">parallel</code> which runs <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cp</code> on all files in multithreaded fashion. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">{}</code> is a placeholder for the current file to be copied to the destination folder, which is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/path/to/destination</code> in this case. And <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--bar</code> is used to display a progress bar.</p> <p>You might have to install <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">parallel</code> package (using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">apt</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pacman</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dnf</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">yum</code> or whatever package manager your distro has) if its not already installed. Its available in all main line linux distros.</p> <p>I learned this trick during my job as a backend developer. It can save you some time if you are trying to copy millions of large files from one drive to another. Sometimes, it can bring the copy / move time to hours from days and to days from weeks!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="linux"/><category term="backend story"/><category term="how to"/><category term="linux"/><category term="copy"/><category term="files"/><category term="move"/><category term="concurrently"/><category term="housekeeping"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes, you need to copy or move files from one drive to another. Copying or moving files using cp / mv one by one can take considerable time some times days and weeks depending upon number of files, size of individual file and disk speed.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">نکاح</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2023/nikah/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="نکاح"/><published>2023-01-01T06:35:23+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T06:35:23+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2023/nikah</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2023/nikah/"><![CDATA[<div dir="rtl" align="right"> نکاح <br/><br/> میں جو معاشرے میں نظر دوڑاتا ہوں <br/> ہر طرف عریانی و بے حیائی پاتا ہوں <br/><br/> حرام سے بچنے کا سبب چاہتا ہوں <br/> نکاح کی نیت جب بناتا ہوں <br/><br/> والدین کو حقیقت بتلاتا ہوں <br/> کہ میں نیک اہلیہ اور سادہ نکاح چاہتا ہوں <br/><br/> گرچہ چند پیسے ہی کماتا ہوں <br/> سادہ کھاتا ہوں نظر جھکاتا ہوں <br/><br/> دل میں یہ خواہش جو پالتاہوں <br/> پوری ہو، دعا میں اللہ سے مانگتا ہوں <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><category term="urdu"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[نکاح میں جو معاشرے میں نظر دوڑاتا ہوں ہر طرف عریانی و بے حیائی پاتا ہوں حرام سے بچنے کا سبب چاہتا ہوں نکاح کی نیت جب بناتا ہوں والدین کو حقیقت بتلاتا ہوں کہ میں نیک اہلیہ اور سادہ نکاح چاہتا ہوں گرچہ چند پیسے ہی کماتا ہوں سادہ کھاتا ہوں نظر جھکاتا ہوں دل میں یہ خواہش جو پالتاہوں پوری ہو، دعا میں اللہ سے مانگتا ہوں]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">جیب</title><link href="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2022/kiyun-apni-jeeb-maal-se-tou-bharta-hy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="جیب"/><published>2022-10-31T17:27:33+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T17:27:33+00:00</updated><id>https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2022/kiyun-apni-jeeb-maal-se-tou-bharta-hy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://iamtalhaasghar.github.io/blog/2022/kiyun-apni-jeeb-maal-se-tou-bharta-hy/"><![CDATA[<div dir="rtl" align="right"> جیب <br/><br/> پڑوس میں تیرے یتیم سسکتا ہے <br/> اپنی جیب مال سے تو بھرتا ہے <br/><br/> یاں چار پیسے پکڑا کے <br/> خامخواہ تو اکٹرتاہے <br/><br/> روزے نمازاں حج <br/> بس انکو صرف دین سمجھتا ہے <br/><br/> جس پہ تیرا چلے بس <br/> خوب اس کمزور پہ تو کڑکتا ہے <br/><br/> گزر جاتا ہے قبرستان کو دیکھ کر <br/> قلب تیرا نہیں لرزتا ہے <br/><br/> ہڑپ کر جائیں گے تیرا سب کچھ <br/> جنہیں تو اپنا کہتا ہے <br/><br/> رب فرماتا ہے جو تجھے <br/> وہ چھوڑ کے باقی سب کرتا ہے <br/><br/> چھوٹ حاصل ہے ابھی تجھ کو <br/> جان لے ہر نفس موت کو چکھتا ہے <br/><br/> انسان جو سدھرتا ہے <br/> نار سے وہی بچتاہے <br/><br/> ہر فرد ہے معاشرے کا ایسے <br/> اللہ سے ہر کوئی تو نہ ڈرتا ہے <br/><br/> حرام کما کر حج کرتا ہے <br/> بے شرمی کی بھی حد کرتا ہے <br/><br/> پڑوس میں تیرے یتیم سسکتا ہے <br/> اپنی جیب مال سے تو بھرتا ہے <br/><br/> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poetry"/><category term="urdu"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[جیب پڑوس میں تیرے یتیم سسکتا ہے اپنی جیب مال سے تو بھرتا ہے یاں چار پیسے پکڑا کے خامخواہ تو اکٹرتاہے روزے نمازاں حج بس انکو صرف دین سمجھتا ہے جس پہ تیرا چلے بس خوب اس کمزور پہ تو کڑکتا ہے گزر جاتا ہے قبرستان کو دیکھ کر قلب تیرا نہیں لرزتا ہے ہڑپ کر جائیں گے تیرا سب کچھ جنہیں تو اپنا کہتا ہے رب فرماتا ہے جو تجھے وہ چھوڑ کے باقی سب کرتا ہے چھوٹ حاصل ہے ابھی تجھ کو جان لے ہر نفس موت کو چکھتا ہے انسان جو سدھرتا ہے نار سے وہی بچتاہے ہر فرد ہے معاشرے کا ایسے اللہ سے ہر کوئی تو نہ ڈرتا ہے حرام کما کر حج کرتا ہے بے شرمی کی بھی حد کرتا ہے پڑوس میں تیرے یتیم سسکتا ہے اپنی جیب مال سے تو بھرتا ہے]]></summary></entry></feed>